[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
e-r. SC radio is brought to you by the
it computer society and by It software
Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Joan proni and today
we'll be discussing developer
productivity with Hans doctor Hans is a
software engineer and the creator of the
gradel build tool is the founder of link
the company maintaining and developing
Gradle and which is behind also the
velocity a developer productivity
platform Hans welcome to the show is
there anything I miss that you would
like to add no I think it was a great
introduction thanks for having me
javanni and looking forward to our
conversation today I'm very excited
about it well me too the pleasure is
mine I'm very excited as well I find
this a very interesting subject so let's
start what is developer
productivity you start with a hard one
yeah so for me the developer
productivity is a theoretical uh
potential for how productive a developer
can be right and then there is the
actual productivity of a developer right
and for me the developer productivity is
about how close is the actual
productivity to the maximum productivity
your development team could provide to
you so in in intuitive terms what we
mean with productivity is kind of number
of feature develop per unit of time is
something else yes I mean you know
there's the whole Space framework right
I think it is multi-dimensional right so
for me every metric that we can quantify
is only a reflection right or a
hypothesis right how this could affect
the actual productivity right I think we
cannot reduce
productivity to a metric what we can do
though there are a lot of metrics that
indicate that your actual productivity
is far from your maximum productivity so
when you know the feedback cycle times
are two hours when you know every second
build fails with flaky test right and
you have a lot of unnecessary
interruptions you know there is a huge
impediment right that reduces your
actual productivity and that is what we
are focusing on right what are the
roadblocks what is by definition right
affecting negatively the productivity
let's say if a development team Works in
a perfect environment right then kind of
From perspective then the Machinery has
done its job right that's what we are
focusing on but then to measure what is
really productivity I don't think at the
moment we have the metric only let's say
in thought experiments yes if someone
doesn't commit any code it's probably
over a year you know there's probably
not much productivity but but otherwise
all those metrics that you talked about
could be gained when we talk about
productivity developer productivity now
there is this old field maybe I don't
think it's very new but certainly now
seems to be gaining more traction that
developer productivity engineering yes
yeah and what is this about it's about
finding methods to to improve this
developer productivity yes so the way I
look at it yeah in theory it's not new
for all practical purposes it's new and
why I say it's new I think when you look
10 or 15 years back right the people who
worked on productivity let's say the
people who worked on Ci or the people
who worked on build systems right or on
the builds right were considered not
good enough to work on a production code
so that's why I would challenge it a
little bit it's not new I think as a
discipline in software it was a
completely esoteric and Niche thing
hardly any organization focused on and
appreciated right so that has
fortunately changed right and DPE right
so there are many dimensions that affect
developer productivity right could be
the food in the cafeteria right or you
know many many things but that is not
what DPE is focusing on on all the
dimensions right DPE focuses on what I
think is the biggest impediment to
developer productivity and that is the
tool chain definitely in an Enterprise
context right there's a lot of other
important vectors that affect it but
that is at the heart of the I would call
it a developer productivity crisis that
we're in right that we slowly Awakening
to that is at the heart of it and DPE is
a practice right that tries to
professionalize how we look at the
developer tool chain and how we improve
it okay and now why is developer
productivity so important because the
actual productivity is far far far from
where it could be so there is a huge
waste right if that weren't the case
then we wouldn't need to have that
conversation but the reality is that
there is a transformational opportunity
for organizations right to get order of
magnitude improvements when it comes to
the output or at least many factors of
improvement right of their code output
if they invest into this area and some
organizations are showing that this is
possible right that's that's why it's so
important that's why I'm intrigued
working in this area because it's
transformational in my opinion yeah okay
yeah I agree that there is a lot of
waste in software development in many
projects I mean I've seen many of those
cases where we waste time and effort and
yeah and there is a lot that can be done
to improve the situation but now I've
got also another question because when I
think productivity I'm thinking also
about developer experience they were you
know you mentioned the tool chain so
what is the relationship between you
know developer productivity and
developer experience yes I think is at
the heart of the developer experience
crisis if you like is the developer
productivity I mentioned this wonderful
book by Ilia Brien one of the great
physicists of the last century he calls
it man's new dialogue with nature the
way he looked at is right as a scientist
you formulate a hypothesis right and
then you enter a dialogue with nature
via experiments to get feedback on that
hypothesis as a developer right we write
code which is a hypothesis and then we
need to enter a DI dialogue with the
tool chain hey compiler hey unit test
hey functional test hey regression test
right what do you think about this
hypothesis right give me feedback right
is it doing what it's supposed to do is
it breaking something is it fast enough
right all of that right and that dialog
is at the heart of what we're doing and
now we come to the experience question
right when I started coding c64 right
back in the days right it was like you
know my print hello world right was fast
there was no waiting so I could
formulate my hypothesis I would get
instant feedback and I don't know if I
would have gotten into programming if I
had the experience of a Enterprise
developer nowadays oh it takes 20
minutes to get any kind of feedback 20
half of the time the feedback is not
correct right that would have destroyed
all the fun where I got hooked up in
software development because it's the
flow right hypothesis feedback
hypothesis feedback let's try this let's
try this I have this question right and
that's so much fun when can move quickly
with that and when you are now bombarded
with a slow unreliable tool chain it's
the one of the most frustrating things
in the world and it takes so much fun
out of the job furthermore right you
have pressure to deliver and the space
framework people write a lot about that
right they say when the impediments are
so strong then the only way you can
deliver what is expected of you is by
doing heroics basically burning yourself
out right doing for extra hours to even
get there kind of to be expected stuff
done so and those two things the flow
right the instantaneous experience
between hypothesis and feedback plus the
pressure to deliver and then having a
blunt knife right that I think both
there's nothing that affects the
experience more than that in a negative
way in the life of a software
development in most environments right
okay now let's talk about you know the
key factors affecting productivity Sur
you mention already the tool chain maybe
you mention in passing slow builds or
long feedback loops basically the two
are there other factors that affect
productivity for developers because I
was thinking about you know things that
sometimes you mention some of your talks
like cognitive load or maybe other
things like I don't know well we'll talk
maybe a bit more later about this but
for example things that have not much to
do with developers with the developers
as in with the writing the code or
creating the system maybe you know
unclear requirements things like this
yes so I would say sure the or the
codebase is in a really bad state right
and now you you have to work on this
right or toxic work environment I mean
which is not probably a complete
exception right so yeah 100% there are
many factors so let's go into the
cognitive Direction the brain is the I
would say at the leadership level is not
a very well understood production means
for code right and there are a lot of
naive assumptions right that I think uh
create negative outcome for the
organizations what do I mean with that
right so when you look at what
Neuroscience tells us right there are
two types of cognitive activity right
one is where you have uh pre-established
neural Pathways right completely learned
cognitive activities like so for example
professional chess players when they do
the opening of a chess match right they
don't have to think much right you can
wake them up at 3m. in the morning and
they will do a right opening move right
usually and because this is learned they
don't have to think about it and other
things is like when we are crossing a
street and we're looking in the right
direction unless we're in England and I
don't have to think about it oh where do
I need to look right those are could be
very complex cognitive activities but
they're completely learned right so and
then we have activities that require
cognitive control and those are the
really interesting one cognitive control
activities are where we know the goal
where we look at the inputs but we don't
know yet how we get there like in the
middle game of a chess match right there
are exponential opportunities there's
nothing pre-learned anymore right so you
need to look at the inputs and what do
I'm trying to achieve right and then you
need to find a way right to get to this
goal and there is a lot of research
around that in Neuroscience so what you
have to do is you have to dynamically
create a model in your prefrontal cortex
where you model the inputs where you
model the goals and then you figure out
how to get there right and all the
valuable coding activity Falls in that
area you need cognitive control is not a
pre-learned thing right you have a
requirement and now you want to have a
certain outcome with software now you
need to think about how to achieve that
right so and the activities that require
mental activities that require cognitive
control they lead to cognitive fatigue
right so and now what does it mean in
the context of developer productivity
right ideally right I have a 100%
conversion of cognitive fatigue in code
right I start in the morning I have the
perfect environment and all my cognitive
fatigue gets basically converted right
into great code for the organization
right that would be ideal and then after
8 hours or whatever I go home I'm
fatigued but you know I got paid for
that fatigue and the company has
hopefully you know a lot of good code
right that creates business value right
so and now the way I look at this a lot
of nonproductive stuff that is happening
that is accelerating cognitive fatigue
without getting any business value out
of that so if I'm understanding your
point correctly of course there is this
cognitive load and cognitive fatigue
because I mean what we do is
Transforming Our thinking into to
something the transform a machine I
guess and you say this kind of the tool
chain we use can be a problem you
mention flaky T but even long feedback
loops so say the build that is too slow
or other factors that something not
working well will actually affect the
feedback loop and this will actually
cause some cognitive fatigue because we
are there waiting for something to
potentially something else okay now what
do you think about the cognitive fatigue
also due to the fact that sometimes you
know maybe we are stretching oursel a
bit too much so for example a lack of
the necessary skills or the fact that
somebody's using for the first time some
tools so a good example is right so many
organizations they now I know Microsoft
is a proponent of that right they're
looking when we hire a new developer
when do we see the first commit the
first pool request right and they cons
this as a primary measure for how good
their onboarding is right and that goes
to what you're saying right how much
cognitive energy do I have to burn to
start getting productive right and I
start working on a new project right so
Microsoft does that so to decide if how
to improve their onboarding process yes
and they have some very interesting data
pran hul he's presenting on that
regularly he's one of the co-authors of
the space paper he's working for
Microsoft research they say the
interesting thing they found is when the
first pull request is earlier then all
the other pull requests that come are
also earlier right so this is for them
now a strong measure that that they will
get that this is a sustainable
productivity gain right is indicated by
an early pull request okay and I think
also you mentioned before about also
code quality so I was wondering also if
the code quality has you know acts as a
potential productivity blocker because
you know especially developers that work
maybe on Legacy systems or systems that
have been created without any test
documentation but in that case it's it's
not about the tool chain that much it's
more about what the material are working
with I'm biased right yes and no right
so what we often see is if you have no
test there's a problem but what we often
see with Legacy project is that the tool
chain experience is terrible but then
the organization saying oh this is not
the future we do not invest into the
tool chain and so let's say you have a
very hairy very coupled tool chain so
you have to do complex refactorings
right let's say to extract some
microservices out of that right and now
when the build takes a long time when
the test quality is poor either the
reliability of the test or the test
coverage right then it's so much harder
to work with a legacy code base yes even
with the best tool chain for a badly
designed Legacy code base that that
affects your productivity but often it
goes together a bad code base with a
really bad tool CH experience and that
makes it so hard to improve it so I'm
biased I always have a tool chain
perspective right that's just kind of
that's why I've seen it so often as the
primary bottl so I agree with you there
are other things here but even here the
tool chain when we look at this in
reality often is a main contributer why
is so hard to work with this Legacy code
base they we got any examples you can
give us of course without naming yeah
yeah so for me and that is probably most
larger companies in the world right it
starts with the reliability of the Fe
feedback which I think emotionally is
even worse than the waiting time so you
have a pool request built and it fails
right so and ask any company right and I
like to do this as a survey when I
present somewhere how often in the last
four weeks you had a failed pull request
build you looked at it and you said I
have no idea why this is failed let's
run it again and if it passes good then
I move on there is so much so we see
many companies where five or 10% even of
their CI builds are failing because of
flakiness in the pipeline and all of
that creates A disruption oh I have to
stop doing what I'm doing I need now to
look why this is failing but it's not
your code that it's failing but you
don't know you just see it's failed is
it my code or is it something in the CI
environment that is not reliable right
and this is just actually have you got
any information about how often is in
the code and how often is the
environment I mean are there any
statistics out there about this yes in
this case so we measure some of that and
that's why I'm saying five to 10% right
of the failures are CI environment
related and that's a big number right
we're talking about you know millions of
bills but the problem but that is not
even let's say it's 50/50 the problem is
right the developer doesn't know that
the worst thing it doesn't know is it
the code or is it the environment and
then what do you do
then you say ah let's file a ticket for
the infrastructure team the
infrastructure team says it's a failing
test what have we to do you look at this
no you have to look at it it's not me
this is a daily dance in 99% of the
Enterprises of the world right I no
organization that have just that have a
whole team on the infrastructure side
working on triing failed CI builds
developers five tickets for we're
talking about 10 20,000 tickets a year
right it's terrible and then the
developers they need to get they want to
merge their poll request so they're
stuck they need to wait until the ticket
is looked at right and the problem is
the percentage is high enough right if
the percentage that developers that they
think it's very likely that it's not my
code right and then they pass it on so
the number is very high right of those
of Pipeline flakiness and it's creating
so many disruptions so much waste it's
one of the biggest problem that we're
seeing out there and hugely frustrating
for everyone involved yeah to me from
what you say seems that the Machinery
there can be either of help if it works
well let's say with the Legacy code if
you have build pipelines and build tools
and everything and you know maybe
tooling for a factoring that actually
work well can enable you to improve the
code base but if they are flak or don't
work well they actually wors in the
situation kind of amplifiers in a sense
Joanie and now now an interesting thing
is right and again I guarantee you that
every company in the world this is
happening every day your cild fail to
put P request build you run it again
it's green okay this can be merged so
there obviously is flakiness right you
haven't changed the input now the result
is different now it works it's green but
you made a good point in many cases they
don't know do I now ship a flaky product
to my customers or do I just deal with a
flaky CI pipeline we don't know the
customer will discover
that right and this is happening every
day many many times how does the team
structure affect productivity I mean not
the single team when you are in a
multiple team situation are there any
effects on developer productivity
directly measurable yes so when you're
saying multiple teams need to work
together on a certain software
deliverable yes yes so that is a very
interesting question right because you
could argue isn't that then one team you
know what I mean yeah right so are you
talking about time zones right because
for me if they're all working together
we should look at them as one team what
I'm thinking of let's say a team like
people that work on the same service
yeah a team of say 8 10 people yeah
usually these teams are around what in
between five and 10 one team but then we
have the situation of teams so you have
two or three or four or five or 10 or
hundreds I've seen I've work in projects
with really hundreds and so each of
these group these teams of 10 people
work on a subset of the bigger system
yeah but all these teams together pretty
much create the entire system system and
so I was wondering if this kind of the
structure of this setup can actually
affect productivity as well and tell you
when I com in from because I've seen
situations of teams waiting for other
teams to be done with their work this is
one example oh so it's a very
interesting topic right and it leads us
again to the tool chain to a degree
right because how is this work organized
so for example do you work all in one
repository or do you have now many
repositories that integrate somehow and
for example one problem we're seeing
right so with the whole microservices
movement I think things went over the
top and people started to create many
many many repositories right which is a
pretty heavyweight abstraction right
with very small amounts of code and now
you have to sync the work between all
those repositories right and you have a
very complex dependency craft because
now all the output is versioned
independently right that complexity has
created a lot of problems right another
thing is in that situation you have
described right when you have many many
repositories so let's say you are
producing a library that is consumed by
a lot of other teams right in the
organization or service doesn't matter
right so what is really a problem is so
now you change something how do you make
sure that you haven't broken the
consumers you don't even know your
consumers in that world right you know
the stuff you are consuming you have no
idea who is consuming you so now you
basically you change something
and now the consumers have to run into
problems right and let you know because
the test you are running because you
don't know your consumers you're only
testing your stuff right you know that
test your functionality but not how your
change is affecting the consumers right
if everything wear in one repository
right that would automatically happen
you would run all the test of all the
consumers all the producers right and
then they green and everything works so
the microservices world has really
created problems right in that respect
as I've just described and it makes
collaboration more difficult maybe those
problems I think you know are solvable
problems you know because with
microservices if you really want to use
them is you can always have versioning
of the interface the API yeah so it's
like you have version one you create
version 1.1 or version two depending on
and so you can of course serve the old
consumers and the new ones but this
creates additional work probably because
you need to manage versioning of the
apis and potentially additional tests
because you have to keep testing
different versions of the MPI and then
come up with deprecation mechanisms and
all sorts of stuff I agree with you it's
solvable I'm just saying it has created
complexity right for having teams
working you know in multiple
repositories that has created
productivity issues so kind of yes I'm
not saying it's not solvable right but
it has definitely created integration
problems that makes that work less
efficient right otherwise I think
another area right is that people have
different when different teams have
different development phos right so that
is now now I'm going to reverse right
let's say you work in one repository
right and with people that have very
different perspectives on testing right
so for example you have now team members
that say I don't care about flaky
test right and basically you're now
running a build and they're now always
test failing right that are not your
test but you cannot get it through the
pipeline right if those tests are
failing and you now have members maybe
in a different team that work on the
same Repository that just say oh just
ignore it just merge it anyhow for
example right that is another thing
where we see a lot of frustration that
there is just not a joint development
philosophy and because it's different
teams with different leadership you can
also not escalate easily right with them
to fix that so that is definitely
something that can be very frustrating
in that situation I guess that the
Machinery has some limitations of what
can do because there is an element of
actually people agreeing on something
absolutely this is where the tool chain
can only say I wouldn't say the tool
chain this is where you want no I fully
agree with you but what we need here at
least as a potential way to I wouldn't
say to solve it but to kind of pinpoint
the problem is let's say you're now in a
situation where you're going to uvp and
saying man those flaky tests right for
that that are introduced by a subset of
the group is killing us right and then
the answer would be well how often is
that a problem and then what do you
think how many people would tell you hey
we had so and so many flaky tests over
the last 30 days no one and then it
becomes a gutfield and the other team is
saying oh they're exaggerating it's not
that much of a problem right so the lack
of observability so so I would say if
you have strong you can derive very
interesting data from the tool chain
that can point to
organizational problems and it allows
you to quantify them versus making it a
a finger pointing exercise that that is
argu from the guts I can tell you that
in a very large scale project that I
consulted for years ago had such a
problem with the flaky tests that they
decided that if more than 90% of the
tests were passing they declared the
product good for release but there was
an additional problem that was this 90%
was not always the same test because the
flakiness so okay was the total
percentage but the test failing could be
different test each time so it was
really a Gumble yes and I think and the
other aspect of that is then it really
demotivates people to write test yes
yeah I agree I agree but I agree good
Machinery good observability can help in
figuring out well at least in
highlighting the organizational problems
and then of course if you have a
dysfunctional organization nothing will
happen in any case but then it's time
maybe to leave yeah when you have a
chance I can ask you also in your
experience you know what are some key
metrics or indicators the teams can use
to measure productivity effectiv I think
for me so going back right to the
dialogue with the tool chain right
I think how many dialogues the
developers do is almost like a survey
every day how much you like your tool
chain and how high the tax you mentally
think you are paying for getting
feedback so and this is fascinating
right I mean we all know this horror
stories right we know one organization
still big enterprise software company
their turnaround time for a full
feedback cycle is 24 hours 24 hours
right and and everyone understands
that's a disaster right or three hours
or two hours right so that is where
everyone emotionally understands that's
terrible to wait so long for feedback
okay when you mention feedback here you
mean a feedback on say a pull request
feedback on feedback on a pull request
good question yes because they have very
different level of feedback thanks for
for asking that so okay now we did some
research right with projects that are in
a much healthier state right so one
example was we had an organization they
one team was having a one minute build
the other team similar tool chain a 4
minute build and the team with the and
both sounds like what's your problem
right that's great four minutes hey
who's complaining about that and they
wen't complaining about it but what we
could see is that the team with the one
minute build time had twice as many
builds and test Cycles than a team with
the four-minute Bill time so the 4minute
bill time was already a tax they were
less willing to pay right then the team
with the one minute Bill time and that's
I think where we as an industry right
need to develop yes we have all those
nightmares hours and everything is
terrible but even if things is in a
pretty good State at least from a
current perspective right Improvement
still makes a lot of sense so that is
another thing that Microsoft has
basically done some serious research on
where they are saying we can now
correlate basically every second of
improved feedback sign typ cycle time
goes into more code right anyhow so I
think this kind of how often do you ask
for feedback is for me a very important
metric and the difference we see between
organizations and teams are astonishing
two orders of magnitude right sometimes
right how often you ask for feedback
right and that is one metric that I
think is a key is a key metric basically
so here we are talking about well the
feedback loop for pool requests how long
it takes then the the bill time as well
it also local bills right how often you
run local bills yeah your pre-commit
build before you even submit a pool
request right okay and is that also
frequency of commits is it a good metric
or it's a very good metric right because
there is a really toxic correlation the
longer your build time the bigger is the
change set of your pull request because
hey I don't want to pay this tax just 50
flaky tests I have to deal with it takes
ages then I have to I have to deal with
all this stuff this is a flat tax right
so let me get a bigger change set going
to make it worthwhile right and the
problem is with all of that even with
the long build time right the happy path
is not so much a problem if your builds
are always succeeding right you have
large change sets you have a long build
time it's not so much of a problems fire
and forget right they're always
succeeding right everything is good but
unfortunately they don't now you have
flakiness combined with a very large
change set right I mean the debugging
nightmare that is causing right because
there's so many dimensions that are now
responsible right so it's a huge problem
yes so I think number of commits a lot
of commits Small Change sets walking to
the pipeline is for me one of the most
important Health metrics okay can I ask
you you know some maybe let's say of the
CU numbers that you think are good
numbers like you know what is your
experience what have you seen in the
best companies for example that use pull
request how long is the feedback loop
you know we are talking minutes hours
days I would say we see many
organizations where when you take
everything into account the flakiness
how often you have to run it the tickets
you file until they're fixed because you
see I buil green again right it is of
hours right and for the best companies
it depends of course right but this is
in the area of minutes so that's where
I'm saying there's really two orders of
magnitude right within the I would say
ignoring the extremely pathological
cases right where this is even worse
Yeah well yeah I've seen pathological
cases of really one or two months for a
PO request of course then when you merge
that is a hell to merge anything because
because so you're making a very good
point right because the big change sets
now the likelihood of major merge
conflicts right and that is for me the
worst thing in the world merge conflicts
are just oh my God right actually now
that you're talking about pool request
and magic and have you got any maybe
with your tools Matrix or have you seen
any Matrix with your customers around
maybe comparing things that do if you
have found any do that do part per
programming and trunk based development
compared to team that maybe do more pool
request and more solo working have you
come across any interesting numbers no
unfortunately we haven't started to
instrument that so that would be super
interesting right to look at that with
different types of development
philosophies right or approaches that
would be super interesting right so one
thing the story I wanted to share is
there was this company and it's a while
ago right but they had a big monor repo
and a buil time was 6 to 7 hours right
if it passed and Leadership was saying
we need to do scrum we need to have
weekly Sprints right and I said okay
let's do this right and the problem was
they were not even able usually if they
were lucky they got one working build a
week and that's your point it took them
month right so and sometime and the only
way often they got a working build for a
week they had to tell everyone freeze no
commits anymore and then how do you do
scrum right and then the testing team
had nothing to do initially right and
then when they were getting close to
their release date it was like all help
broke loose it's exactly what you're
saying so the whole idea hey we want to
introduce scrum when you have that kind
of feedback Cycles right and before you
get a pull request through forget about
it right yeah well you to do to make
some deeper changes to to everything
pretty much yes exactly exactly okay so
just now before move on I'm interested
so in terms of interesting metrics we
said the frequency of commits is an
interesting one that length of the back
Loop for pool request seems to be
another good one are there any other
that you suggest as in you know
generally good ones to look at for me
super super important is how early do
people ask for feedback right because we
want to shift left right we want to we
want that developers work in small
increment and ask as early when we say
how early they ask for feedback what do
you mean exactly with the asking for
feedback I will explain so for me a very
good metric is number of pull request
build versus number of local builds
right so if we see that developers stop
running local builds often because the
experience is to do this right then they
say ah it's such a pain right let's do
this on CI which means they will do it
much less often and later then you're
Shifting the whole thing to do right
right or because maybe the machine when
they run their tests have to run it on
their machine and then it consumes so
much load from the machine that they
cannot work in the IDE right that is
something so you want to shift them left
and everyone says every organ ization
yeah shifting left is great we have to
do this this is our philosophy the
reality is though it's shifting right at
this point in time right because the
code bases are growing right so I think
it's super important that people take
care of the local feedback experience
and it's often completely ignored
because you have zero data about it yeah
that that is quite interesting actually
it's quite interesting and I think you
know to add a bit to this point I've
seen situations where in theory the
company management wanted to do the
right thing okay in practice they gave
developers underpowered machines that
were not able to do much so maybe not
enough disc not enough memory not enough
processor power and so I've seen
situations where for the developers
pretty much a local build was not really
an appealing option yes I can tell you a
funny story right and so before I tell
but I think it's a funny story but then
you need to think about so I I really
think that the mabox the MX uh process a
game changer for development right and
they really expanded what is possible to
do on a local machine significantly
right so that is very exciting right and
but there are still limits obviously so
that is where I think Technologies need
to come in like hey you run your build
locally but you can run your test right
fully trans you just run your Maven your
cradle your spbt whatever build right
and but the tests we take and run them
on distributed agents right to take that
load away from you or there is Facebook
has a Pioneer that right there is
technology like predictive test
selection where we use an AI model right
or where you use an AI model that
predicts hey for this change let's say
900 out of your thousand test with 99%
likelihood will succeed they're not
sensitive to that change so let's weaken
the quality gate a little bit right but
with the advantage that you get much
faster feedback with much less resources
so there's really interesting stuff and
that's where DPE comes in right to think
about this to model this to create this
kind of backend right so that you can
actually get early feedback and the
funny story I wanted to share there is a
company that their build time was going
50 minutes 20 minutes 25 minutes and the
developers were supposed to always run
local builds before they commit and push
something at one point they were
escalating to the VP we cannot do this
any anymore it takes way tooo much time
right and you will like that story so
then they established a task force right
and task force was trying to fix it and
the goal was to get it under 5 minutes
and they got it down I don't know from
28 to 22 minutes with some improvements
it was far away from the 5 minutes and
then they came up with the solution and
they were quite convinced that this was
a good solution they said hey just stop
running the test locally and boom
everything was under five minutes and
they were pretty proud
about it and I was like okay whatever
right
great it doesn't seem to be a good
solution it does right okay and now
let's talk about steps to improve
productivity in a company so say an
organization they have problems maybe
they're not measuring much at the moment
but they have the feeling that
everything is slow they want to go
faster this is a typical thing in most
of organizations everybody wants to go
faster so what are the first steps you
would suggest it's very easy and now
we're coming back to the management so
the thing that was eye openening for me
years back was when so Android is a you
know Mobile in general is a more complex
platform than doing let's say
microservices with Java for the back end
right so because there's so much stuff
that needs to be done for building
mobile applications build time is
particularly a problem right and then
the Google Android team developed then a
lot of improvements right for making
this faster but then quite a few of
those improvements required that you
needed to reconfigure and redo your
build and some things in your code right
to get benefits from this and they did
it because all the service were the
developers saying that's our biggest
problem by far now they've offered
significant Improvement and now less
developers than they thought we're
making use of those right and then they
did a big survey right why is this the
case and the developer said our biggest
problem is to make the business case to
the management that we get resources to
do this
I see so and let me give you a concrete
example right how it works in most
organizations so many organizations move
to eeral CI right let's always throw the
CI environment away before you run the
next build so all your local state your
local caches are thrown away and it's
culturally maybe we have time to go into
this right but why this happened and and
not what but the CI build time has
drastically increased because of that
including pull request build and a big
part of that is now downloading all the
dependencies over and over again so you
have no idea how many people came to me
and said oh dependency download time is
a big problem and then I was asking the
most naive question in the world well
what is your average dependency bound
time we don't know across the board it's
not a single organization almost on a
planet that could tell you what is the
actual dependency download time although
everyone is complaining about so if
someone would come to me and my company
would say man dependency download time
is a huge problem we need five people to
fix it I would say well how big of a
problem is it right and then oh we don't
know everyone is complaining about it
and that puts you in a paralysis state
so am I now willing to invest into this
when I cannot quantify it so then it's
maybe let's put half a person on the
problem right but the reality is now
when we measure this at some of those
organizations we see easily 30% of the
DCI build time is just downloading
dependence and now you can have a
conversation with the leadership saying
look this is 30% that cost us compute
resources because the C machines are
idle while downloading dependencies
right it cost us 1 million minutes per
whatever period of time right now you
can have a conversation now you can make
a business case so my the answer for me
is therefore observability is everything
don't even start on anything gutfield
wise you need to measure to see how big
the problem is and the particular
problem and then to measure what is the
Improvement right so people think always
thinking oh there are some silver
bullets right so let's introduce a new
technology with without any
observability so for me it all starts
with observability with instrumenting
and that's how we would do performance
Improvement of an application right but
that is the kind of immaturity we still
have in that area of the software
industry right that we not applying best
practices we would apply in other areas
am I correct if you if I interpret this
as we developers technical people should
actually do our homework first get the
numbers and then go when we complain go
there with appropriate information so we
can have the conversation 100% otherwise
it's just developers whining again all
those developers right they're never
happy there's another it's one of my
favorite stories right because it shows
the cultural kind of mismatch so we were
talking with the big car maker they
wanted to talk about developer
productivity and I'm kind of I mean it's
a little bit mean I always ask those
questions right very simple how many
feedback Cycles do you developers run
per day what is the average time of them
and how often do they fail I mean the
most innocent simple questions you can
imagine and the answer I was getting is
we don't know in this case the answer
was well we need to do a survey to
figure this out right and then I said
well if I would go to any of your
factories and would ask how long is
assembly part a right taking to get from
there to there how long is it sitting in
a shelf and I want to get an answer on
that in five minutes the person would be
fired it would be culturally a disgrace
people would be ashamed it's even Beyond
it's Beyond just you know rational it
would be like this is not who we are
right and that's where we need to get as
a software industry for our own stuff
you put it perfectly right we have to do
our homework you know when it comes to
that also one other thing I was thinking
at least I mean you can tell me this if
it matches your experience in my
experience and and apparently also in
literature there is a lot of work that
developers do so let's say that they
have the perfect Machinery yeah that
everything works fine but then if you
look at the literature and well at least
also in my experience and probably you
have seen this with some of your
customers is even for the features we
produce usually there is a kind of parto
rule thing that is pretty much 20% of
the features we produce are the ones
that are use the remaining
80% we could have avoided them so I was
wondering from a management perspective
maybe looking at that first which is
probably a bit more difficult than
measuring developers productivity with
the Machinery look at that could be
another attack point because that would
free up some productivity for developers
to do something more useful yes so I
absolutely agree and the question is I
think the likelihood of this to happen
that you do not the most important stuff
increases with cognitive fatigue right
if you're fatigued you rather do
incremental stuff right something you
feel familiar with than thinking about
what is actually the most important
thing right so I mean there could be
many reasons
for that but fatigue can be one major
reason I see it even in our company
right when you're fatigued you don't see
the forest for the trees it's hard to
kind of think about the bigger picture
because that requires a lot of cognitive
control right so if you are in a
fatigued organization I think it's very
unlikely that they work on the most
important stuff so if I understand
correctly you're saying that fatigas
acts as a kind of an amplifier for this
problem again because yes exactly it's
like brings you to look at the familiar
or in general you spend less time
thinking about what is important and
what is good so one thing I found
fascinating is how do they measure
cognitive fatigue in a cognitive science
experiments right and because they're
still not 100% sure of the biological
root cause of fatigue right they only
know it exists right so how they measure
it is in many of those experiments right
so let's say they let you do a lot of
context switching right to kind of
accelerate fatigue right some math
problem here then a word problem here
you get the idea right and then they
always give you two choices right one is
low cognitive effort low reward the
other is high cognitive effort High
reward so let's say $10 if you solve the
difficult problem $1 if you solve the
easy problem and when people start
switching from difficult to easy that's
the indication they're now fatigue and
that kind of correlates well to what you
just described right in software okay
yeah never thought about this from this
angle that is quite interesting now
another question now so we talk about
management and developers and how to do
how W work to put things to managers now
let's say that in a company people that
said okay we'll do some developer
productivity engineering and then we put
the tools in place to measure everything
and to have the metrics that are of
interest to us to improve the situation
yeah who owns this metric who owns the
developer productivity as a concept in
an organization developers managers both
yes it has to be both so what we see and
that is a very promising thing thing
right even in the let's say non-tech
industry let's say Financial world right
we now see a developer experience and
developer productivity metrics have
c-level ownership I think that's
extremely important otherwise you're not
getting anywhere right if that is not at
the highest level considered strategic
it will always be deprioritized right so
I think that is super important but and
that leads us to an interesting topic so
we talked about metrics right that let's
say are now owned even at at sea level
right that indicate improvements to
developer productivity I think what has
happened in the last couple of years
that metrics were perceived as
measurements how good the developers are
so basically there is now a sea- Lev
team that now starts instrumenting
developer productivity to find out who
are the bad developers like naively said
or the non-productive ones right and use
that then also to make personal
decisions right and I think not even
talking about the ethical aspect here
I'm just talking about the economic
aspect here this is absolutely wrong
right because when that starts happening
those valuable metrics let's say number
of builds people will start gaming it at
the moment people are honest with how
many builds they're running it's a
survey about how good is toolchain
experience when they learn about oh this
is now how we're getting measured right
people will start gaming and completely
destroy the value of that metric so
that's why I think there need to be some
form of contract yes those metrics are
very important to us but we understand
that we cannot draw uh naive conclusions
you know to the quality of the teams or
the developers based on those metrics
but those metrics are important and the
developers need to be part of the metric
discussion to understand what is the
root cause that this metric is bad how
can we improve it so the metric should
be a guideline to improve the machinery
and the environment versus looked at it
hey this is now a tool to measure
how good you are right I think that's
super important in my opinion can I ask
you a question on that so we already
said that your company created a
developer productivity platform this the
velocity so but this question is about
now the this aspect that you just
mentioned are there is there a way to
put in these platforms Provisions so
that it's difficult to trace back to
individuals what the metric you know
Trace back the metrics to individual
yeah so some company especially in
Europe right they even have legal
requirements to do so and we can hide
all the personal information for example
but I think it's a Pity that we have to
do that and it's there's something
culturally wrong when we have to do this
to protect developers because we lose
very interesting information right I
want the developer to see for themsel
right oh my God right why is everyone
else in my team why am I the one with
the build time that is five times slower
than everyone else oh I'm the only guy
in Singapore right and there is the the
caches are so far away from me right so
there is so much value in being able to
break down the metrics if they are
looked at it from a collaborative
perspective hey we want to improve the
environment right you lose information
but yes there are ways to do that but
you pay a price for that and it's sad
right that you have to do it to protect
developers something is wrong with the
culture in my opinion if that is
necessary right but it is possible yes
yeah I have to say that I've seen in the
past I consultant for a big company on a
big project and there was a major
cultural problem there in terms of trust
and the CTO there mandated that
developers said to do a certain number
of commits per month or else yeah
engineering managers said to do at least
one per month as well because he wanted
an organization of technical people but
it's interesting what happened there was
exactly what you mentioned before so
some people that are not really doing
much development every day because they
were doing other useful work they change
in consequential files you know text
files something that could appear in a
commit because they knew that people
would only look at the number of commits
not what was changed see not the quality
of the work or the particular effect so
that was quite dysfunctional I mean with
all respect to the leadership there but
I mean I think the person in my opinion
that need to get fired is not any one of
the developers right because this is so
obviously stupid and ineffective and
setting the wrong incentives right it's
but yeah and or people know measuring
how much you move your mouse cursor
right there are quite a I know quite a
few organ and with the remote from home
situation right there you heard about it
right the productivity paranoia in the
leadership our people still doing work
or they just hanging out on a patio
right looking at the sunset okay and
then can I ask you let's say that now we
are in a situation where the culture is
fine and we and the teams want to and
the company wants to improve improve
their productivity there in PL s so are
there any pitfalls that the teams
encounter when trying to improve
productivity there was an organization
that had a very successful organization
but they had for legacy reasons they had
a situation where they had tens and tens
of millions of yaml files right so it's
very but it's it sounds very kind of
okay what is interesting here but tens
and tens of millions of yaml files that
they were assembling right in their
archive files right for deployment right
and that made their build time very long
right we're talking about just copying
those the way they did it right and
working with them was taking 15 to 20
minutes right for every you know every
build right so and they were on build
system a I don't even mention any name
it doesn't matter right and then we did
something right we wrote them some logic
to get this time down to seconds with
build system a dramatic right
Improvement I mean obviously right but
then they said oh but we want a micr to
build system B and if we now make build
system a much better then we might lose
the mandate to move to build system be
and we see this all the time they're
holding something hostage so they don't
want to do the low hanging fruit because
then people might say oh this is good
enough right don't do anything more long
term so they were not applying this
change and the migration is taking years
right while people still have to use
build system a and Javan I guarantee you
I see this over and over and over again
people because of the immaturity right
they use a big problem to say oh you can
only solve this by doing something
strategically and then they get amended
to do something strategically although
they could fix it two orders of
magnitude faster but they don't want to
because then they cannot do something
more strategically that is one Pitfall
that I see that seems to be a problem
with the developers themselves the
technical people seems to be they're
more interested in doing something new
than improving something that is already
there working and delivering exactly
exactly a new toy a new Silver Bullet
right absolutely and that is one part
and I agree that is probably more than
50% of the story and then the other part
is that it might be the only way to get
resources let's say for doing something
which they think is actually important
so it's a mix of both but you you make a
very good point yeah I think we are
towards the end of the interview now so
I would ask you to the future you know
how do you see the future of developer
praity engineering evolving yes so when
you look at let's say chemical process
engineering you can study this at every
University there are probably 100
thousands PhD thesises about every
aspect right of got chemical process
engineering so there's a deep cognitive
Roots tremendous body of research of
Empirical research of theoretical
research right and it's in the DNA of
the companies to apply that right that's
what I would be looking for for
developer productivity engineering that
this becomes really also an academic
discipline I mean it's a trillion dollar
industry right and we're treating the
production like it is we building
lemonade stand right I mean seriously
right it's changing now right that's I
think the found the academic foundation
and the depth of thinking and modeling
especially you talked about it AI models
right how do you measure things right I
mean we're just at the beginning right
and Academia is not involved yet
Bridging the Divide from all the
interesting research in cognitive
science to what does it mean for
software development such a body of
research there we're not applying yet
right so those are yeah building this
foundation and then all the rest will
follow right okay and are there any
interesting developments at the moment
you know in your opinion like some
technological advances or improve
methods that we'll see in the shortterm
because what you just mentioned for the
future seems to be more kind of
long-term Vision but is there something
coming in the shorter term in your view
that we don't have yet of course we
cannot finish this podcast right talk
about generative AI right so yeah I
think generative AI is there right and
that I think it increases the pressure
so here's how I look at this right so
let's say you get to win fall from
generative Ai and every developer writes
twice as much code well the code needs
to be built needs to be tested yada yada
yada so the tool chain pressure if the
experience is right now good luck when
everyone writes twice as much code right
and then you will not get that windfall
from generative AI in terms of getting
features to the customer faster etc etc
the other thing I think it will also it
should push us in the following
Direction so imagine we talked about
cognitivity right so let's say there's
an organization where in every aage the
cognitive fatigue sets in 3 hours at
11:00 a.m. right in the morning right so
those people are not going home there is
still busy work to do rename this
refactor this write some simple
algorithms right so which adds some
value although not the 80% value we
talking about before but it adds the 20%
value so now imagine a world that we're
probably getting close to where all this
busy work is done by Ai and what are
those people doing starting from 11:00
a.m. right so I think the companies that
push the cognitive fatigue out right to
later right will generative AI will
increase the competitive Advantage
they're getting from that so that's
something companies should think about
and then what generative AI can do for
the tool chain right to make it easier
to improve the tool chain right one
reason is let's say for example if
everyone had a perfect modularized code
structure it would have a huge benefit
on build times on how can you paralyze
and cach and reuse right dramatic right
but hardly anyone is tackling that
because modularization is just a hairy
issue with the cyclic dependencies and
things like that right so if AI could
tackle some of those hard problems right
to reorganize your tool chain at the
software in a way that it's a much lower
cost that would be amazing right for the
productivity of software developers okay
thank you very much I think we've come
to the end I think we've done a good job
introducing developer productivity
thanks Hans is there anything else that
you would like to mention something that
we missed that you think would be
important to mention no you ask all the
questions that have covered all the
stuff I wanted to share so yeah thanks a
lot this was a great experience from my
side I really enjoyed the conversation
okay thank you Hans for coming to the
show then has been a real pleasure for
me and this is joavan as proni for
software engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r.
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under creative comments
license
2.5 thanks for listening